

Alexandre Chapiro

I am interested in applied perception and psychophysics as related to computational display, as well as image and video processing techniques. In particular, I've worked on topics in stereo 3D, high dynamic range, brightness and color, frame rate and motion, user experience and virtual reality.

Professional Experience

2018-now Apple Inc., Cupertino

Senior Display Help identify and cultivate new display and image processing technologies and

Engineer experiences for future Apple products

affiliation Core Display Incubation Team, managed by Nicolas Bonnier

2017-2018 Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale

Senior Conducted research and obtained experimental results on human perception factors

Researcher relevant to business needs

affiliation Applied Vision Science group, managed by Robin Atkins

2011-2016 Disney Research, Zurich

Researcher Conducted research on novel displays, stereo 3D, high dynamic range, high framerate

and human perception resulting in four patent applications and several publications

affiliation Stereo and Displays group, managed by Aljoša Smolić

Education

2011-2015 **PhD in Computer Science**

institution Federal Institute of Technology Zurich (ETHZ), Zurich, Switzerland

thesis title Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays

affiliation Computer Graphics Laboratory

supervisors Prof. Markus Gross. Co-Advisor: Dr. Aljoša Smolić

2010-2011 Masters' Degree in Applied Mathematics

institution Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics (IMPA), Rio de Janeiro, Brazil

thesis title Improving Mobile Video

affiliation Visgraf laboratory

supervisors Prof. Paulo Cezar Pinto Carvalho. Co-Advisor: Prof. Luiz Velho

2007-2009	Undergraduate Degree in Mathematics
institution	Federal University of Juiz de Fora (UFJF), Juiz de Fora, Brazil
thesis title	An Introduction to Degree Theory
affiliation	Computer Graphics Laboratory
supervisors	Prof. Luiz Faria, Marcelo Bernardes Vieira
2016-2016	Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale
Intern	Conducted research on the human visual system guided by business unit needs
affiliation	Applied Vision Science group, managed by Robin Atkins
	Teaching
Feb.2014	Teaching assistant , Math. Foundations of Computer Graphics and Vision, ETHZ.
to Jun.2014	Graduate class teaching mathematical techniques in visual computing
Feb.2015 to Jun.2015	Teaching assistant , Math. Foundations of Computer Graphics and Vision, ETHZ.
Feb.2012	Teaching assistant, Informatik 1, ETHZ.
to Jun.2012	Undergradute class teaching fundaments of informatics to engineering students
Feb.2013 to Jun.2013	Teaching assistant , <i>Informatik</i> 1, ETHZ.
	Academic Honors
2015	Second youngest PhD to graduate from the CS department at ETH Zurich at 25
2011	Finished 2-year Master's program at the National Institute of Pure and Applied Mathematics in 18 months
2009	Finished 4-year undergraduate program in Mathematics at the Federal University of Juiz de Fora in 3 years with the highest GPA in the graduating class
2007	Ranked 1st in admission examinations, Federal University of Juiz de Fora
2006	Gold Medalist, Brazilian Astronomy Olympiad
2006	Gold Medalist, Brazilian Mathematics Olympiad for Public School Students. 95th place among approximately 5.3 million students
2005	Gold Medalist, Brazilian Mathematics Olympiad for Public School Students. 9th place among approximately 3.8 million students
	Academic Service
Commitee	2019, SIBGRAPI Journal Track International Program Committee.
	2018, SIBGRAPI International Program Committee.
Reviewing	2019, SIGGRAPH, Eurographics.

2018, SIBGRAPI, Eurographics.

2017, SIGGRAPH, Pacific Graphics, IEEE TIP.

2016, SIGGRAPH Asia, Graphics Interface, IEEE TIP, JOSA.

2015, SIGGRAPH, SIGGRAPH Asia, ICIP,IEEE CG&A, IEEE TVCG.

2014, *Pacific Graphics*, *CG Forum*. **2012**. *3DV*.

Awards and Funding

Oct.2011 **Participant**, European Commission Program FP7.

to Oct.2013

Mar.2010 Awarded, Master program fellowship, CNPq.

to Jul.2011

Jan.2009 Awarded, Undergraduate research scholarship, FAPEMIG.

to Dec.2009

Jan.2008 Awarded, Undergraduate research scholarship, CNPq.

to Dec.2008

Mar.2007 Awarded, Scholarship for winners OBMEP 2006 mathematics olympics, CNPq.

to Jan.2008

Mar.2006 Awarded, Scholarship for winners OBMEP 2005 mathematics olympics, CNPq.

to Jan.2007

Jan.2005 Awarded, High-school research scholarship, CNPq.

to Dec.2005

 Obs.: CNPq is the Brazilian national funding agency. FAPEMIG is the funding agency for the state of Minas Gerais, Brazil

Invited Talks and Presentations

invited talk: Cinematic Motion.

NAB show 2018, Las Vegas, invited by Jaclyn Pytlarz

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

IBM 2017, Rio de Janeiro, hosted by Emilio Vital Brazil

invited talk: **Computer Graphics**, (popular lecture).

IF Sudeste MG 2017, Juiz de Fora, hosted by Elena Konstantinova

invited talk: Computer Graphics, (popular lecture).

IF Sudeste MG 2016, Rio Pomba, hosted by Lucas Lattari

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

Dolby Laboratories 2016, Sunnyvale, hosted by Timo Kunkel

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for Novel Displays.

Technicolor 2015, Rennes, hosted by Erik Reinhard

invited talk: Perceptual Enhancements for 3D Displays.

Max Planck Institut 2015, Saarbrucken, hosted by Piotr Didyk

paper talk: Stereo from Shading.

EGSR 2015

paper talk: Perceptual Evaluation of Cardboarding in 3D Content Visualization.

SAP 2015

paper talk: Optimizing Stereo-to-Multiview Conv. for Autostereo. Displays.

Eurographics 2015

Languages

Portuguese Fluent Native speaker

Russian Fluent Native speaker

English Fluent TOEFL iBT 117/120, Cambridge FCE and CAE exams with A grades

Spanish Fluent 3 years of school in Spain

French Advanced Alliance Française DELF diplome - 2005

German Beginner Approximately A2 level

References

Prof. Dr. Markus Gross,

Director of Disney Research Zurich. Full Professor, ETH Zurich.

Prof. Dr. Aljoša Smolić,

SFI Research Professor of Creative Technologies, Trinity College Dublin.

Scott Daly,

Senior Member of Science Staff, Dolby Laboratories, Sunnyvale.

Dr. Tunç Aydın,

Research Scientist, Disney Research Zurich.

Publications

Papers

Influence of Screen Size and Field of View on Perceived Brightness,

ACM Transactions on Applied Perception (TAP), 2018,

Chapiro, A., Kunkel, T., Atkins, R., Daly, S.

Unfolding the 8-bit Era,

European Conference on Visual Media Production 2015,

Zund, F., Berard, P., Chapiro, A., Schmid, S., Ryffel, A., Bermano, A., Gross, M., Sumner, R.

Art-Directable Continuous Dynamic Range Video,

Compters & Graphics, Elsevier, 2015,

Chapiro, A., Aydin, T., Stefanoski, N., Croci, S., Smolic, A., Gross, M.

Video Content and Structure Description Based on Keyframes, Clusters and Storyboards,

IEEE International Workshop on Multimedia Signal Processing, Xiamen-China, 2015,

Junyent, M., Beltran, P., Farre, M., Pont-Tuset, J., Chapiro, A., Smolic, A.

Stereo from Shading,

Eurographics Symposium on Rendering, Darmstadt-Germany, 2015. (E&I track), Chapiro, A., O'Sullivan, C., Jarosz, W., Gross, M., Smolic, A.

Perceptual Evaluation of Cardboarding in 3D Content Visualization,

ACM Symposium on Applied Perception, Vancouver-Canada, 2014. (Short paper), Chapiro, A., Diamanti, O., Poulakos, S., O'Sullivan, C., Smolic, A., Gross, M.

Optimizing Stereo-to-Multiview Conversion for Autostereoscopic Displays,

Eurographics, Strasbourg-France, 2014,

Chapiro, A., Heinzle, S., Aydin, T., Poulakos, S., Zwicker, M., Smolic, A., Gross, M.

Towards Mobile HDR Video,

Eurographics, Llandudno-UK, 2011. (Extended abstract) Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Cicconet, M., Velho, L.

Detection of High Frequency Regions in Multiresolution,

International Conference on Image Processing, Cairo-Egypt, 2009. Mota, V.F., Perez, E.A., Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Vieira, M.B.

High Frequency Assessment from Multiresolution Analysis,

International Conference on Computational Science, Baton Rouge-USA, 2009 Castro, T.K., Perez, E. A., Mota, V. F., Chapiro, A., Vieira, M. B., Freire, W. P.

Patents

Systems and methods for automatic key frame extraction and storyboard interface generation for video,

US Patent US9552520 B1, 2017 (Related to our 2015 paper) Smolic, A., Martin, M., Pont-Tuset, J., Chapiro, A., Guiu, M.

Methods for creating and distributing art-directable continuous dynamic range video,

US20160353164 A1, 2016 (Related to our 2015 paper)

Smolic, A., Chapiro, A., Croci, S., Aydin, T., Stefanoski, N., Gross, M.

Visual salience of online video as a predictor of success,

US20170061235 A1, 2015 (Related to our 2015 poster)

Frey, S., Accardo, AM., Sumner, R., Huber, R., Chapiro, A.

Depth modification for display applications,

US20150348273 A1, 2015 (Related to our 2014 paper) Chapiro, A., Aydin, T., Poulakos, S., Heinzle, S., Smolic, A.

Book Chapters

Discrete Wavelets on Edges,

InTech open publisher, 2011

Chapiro, A., Knop, T., Mota, V., Perez, E., Bernardes, M., Freire W. P.

Posters

The Influence of Visual Salience on Video Consumption Behavior A Survival Analysis Approach,

ACM Web Science, Oxford-United Kingdom, 2015 Huber, R., Scheibehenne, B., Chapiro, A., Frey, S., Sumner, R.

Filter Based Deghosting for Exposure Fusion Video,

SIGGRAPH, Vancouver-Canada, 2011. Student Research Competition Semi-Finalist Chapiro, A., Cicconet, M., Velho, L.

Towards Mobile HDR Video,

International Conference on Computational Photography, Pittsburg-USA, 2011 Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Cicconet, M., Velho, L.

Mountain's Pass Theorem,

Minas-Gerais Meeting of Partial Diferential Equations, Itajuba-Brazil, 2009 Chapiro, A., Pereira, F.

Other

Image Domain Warping for Advanced 3D Video Applications,

IEEE COMSOC MMTC E - Letter, 2014. (Invited letter)

Smolic A., Wang, O., Lang, M., Stefanoski, N., Farre, M., Greisen, P., Heinzle, S., Schaffner, M., Chapiro, A., Sorkine-Hornung, A., Gross, M.

Computational Photography,

IMPA, Rio de Janeiro-Brazil, 2011. (Technical report) Castro, T.K., Chapiro, A., Velho, L.